<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sensors | Zach Perzan</title>
    <link>https://zperzan.github.io/tag/sensors/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://zperzan.github.io/tag/sensors/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Sensors</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://zperzan.github.io/media/icon_hud1d0979e3910d321b321c3c963a9ae6e_14691_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Sensors</title>
      <link>https://zperzan.github.io/tag/sensors/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data-driven water quality modeling</title>
      <link>https://zperzan.github.io/research/sensors/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zperzan.github.io/research/sensors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, hydrologic modeling has relied on a suite of process-based models developed by many different researchers over years or even decades. These models contain a wealth of domain knowledge about contaminant transport &amp;ndash; the physics of water flow and the chemistry of water-rock interactions &amp;ndash; but they are relatively fixed and not designed to handle new streams of incoming data; a calibrated reactive transport model, for example, has to be completely re-calibrated from the beginning if new observations are not in agreement with model predictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent advances in data science and &lt;em&gt;in situ&lt;/em&gt; sensors &amp;ndash; when combined with robust biogeochemical models &amp;ndash; offer a unique opportunity to address this challenge. We have installed a network of solar-powered environmental sensors at sites in Colorado and Wyoming that provide continuous, high-frequency measurements of hydrologic conditions, microbial metabolic activity and key biogeochemical constituents. Remote connection via cellular modem allows us to access this data and update models in real time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are using several techniques to combine the knowledge contained within (process-based) reactive transport models with the flexibility and adaptability of modern machine learning/deep learning models. This includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assimilating sensor data into a basic reactive transport model with an ensemble Kalman filter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Training an LSTM (and now transformers) with data from reactive transport model simulations, then using transfer learning to apply the model to real-world data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The same as above, but using sensor data from other sites across the world&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Augementing sensor training data with generative adverarial networks (GAN) then building a GRU, LSTM, or sequence-to-sequence model&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
