<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Current research | Zach Perzan</title>
    <link>https://zperzan.github.io/research/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://zperzan.github.io/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Current research</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://zperzan.github.io/media/icon_hud1d0979e3910d321b321c3c963a9ae6e_14691_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Current research</title>
      <link>https://zperzan.github.io/research/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling managed aquifer recharge (MAR) in the Central Valley</title>
      <link>https://zperzan.github.io/research/cv-mar/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zperzan.github.io/research/cv-mar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;body&gt;
&lt;video width=&#34;1224&#34; height=&#34;964&#34; loop autoplay muted&gt;
  &lt;source src=&#34;voxel.mp4&#34; type=&#34;video/mp4&#34;&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the coming decades, increased interannual variability in precipitation &amp;ndash; wetter wet years and drier dry years &amp;ndash; will place increased demand on California&amp;rsquo;s network of reservoirs and dams. Though we need additional water storage capacity to store water from rainy years for use during drought years, events like the Oroville Dam disaster highlight the fact that California’s water storage infrastructure is already maxed out. Managed aquifer recharge (MAR) projects &amp;ndash; in which water is intentionally stored in aquifers for later extraction &amp;ndash; have been proposed as a tool to combat this problem; in California’s Central Valley, excess precipitation diverted to MAR sites could recharge aquifers with up to 1.5 km&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; of water per year, approximately 11% of annual groundwater withdrawals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, identifying the most promising MAR sites remains an ongoing challenge. We are using ParFlow &amp;ndash; an integrated hydrologic model capable of simulating both saturated and unsaturated flow &amp;ndash; to understand the processes that control groundwater recharge.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biogeochemical cycling in high-elevation floodplains</title>
      <link>https://zperzan.github.io/research/riverton/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zperzan.github.io/research/riverton/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A long history of uranium mining and weapons development throughout the Cold War has left many mining, milling and testing sites contaminated with radioactive materials like uranium, thorium, and radium, as well as other non-radioactive heavy metals including vanadium, molybdenum, selenium and arsenic. There are nearly 100 such locations &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.energy.gov/lm/sites/lm-sites&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;across the western U.S.&lt;/a&gt; managed by the Department of Energy. The groundwater contaminant plumes at many sites are not dissipating as expected and contamination may persist beyond the 100-year timeframe required for regulatory compliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contaminant plumes at many floodplain mill sites are subject to strong seasonal fluctuations, but the processes behind these variations are not well understood. We are studying uranium transport and the concurrent biogeochemical cycling that occurs during hydrologic perturbations, with research centered around a series of field experiments using artificial groundwater tracers. The tracer tests have immediate relevance to water quality concerns at the field site &amp;ndash; a uranium-contaminated floodplain in Riverton, Wyoming &amp;ndash; but has much broader implications as well. Isotopically labeled nitrate allows us to track denitrification and the production of nitrous oxide (a powerful greenhouse gas), deuterated water (D&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O) could map plant water uptake, and dye infiltration patterns can answer questions regarding unsaturated zone flow.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data-driven water quality modeling</title>
      <link>https://zperzan.github.io/research/sensors/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zperzan.github.io/research/sensors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, hydrologic modeling has relied on a suite of process-based models developed by many different researchers over years or even decades. These models contain a wealth of domain knowledge about contaminant transport &amp;ndash; the physics of water flow and the chemistry of water-rock interactions &amp;ndash; but they are relatively fixed and not designed to handle new streams of incoming data; a calibrated reactive transport model, for example, has to be completely re-calibrated from the beginning if new observations are not in agreement with model predictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent advances in data science and &lt;em&gt;in situ&lt;/em&gt; sensors &amp;ndash; when combined with robust biogeochemical models &amp;ndash; offer a unique opportunity to address this challenge. We have installed a network of solar-powered environmental sensors at sites in Colorado and Wyoming that provide continuous, high-frequency measurements of hydrologic conditions, microbial metabolic activity and key biogeochemical constituents. Remote connection via cellular modem allows us to access this data and update models in real time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are using several techniques to combine the knowledge contained within (process-based) reactive transport models with the flexibility and adaptability of modern machine learning/deep learning models. This includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assimilating sensor data into a basic reactive transport model with an ensemble Kalman filter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Training an LSTM (and now transformers) with data from reactive transport model simulations, then using transfer learning to apply the model to real-world data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The same as above, but using sensor data from other sites across the world&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Augementing sensor training data with generative adverarial networks (GAN) then building a GRU, LSTM, or sequence-to-sequence model&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Novel biosensors for monitoring trace contaminants</title>
      <link>https://zperzan.github.io/research/qube/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zperzan.github.io/research/qube/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most contaminants in water (nitrate, arsenic, mercury and lead, to name a few) can only be measured by manually grabbing a water sample and analyzing it in the lab. This is a time-intensive process. A few companies offer optical sensors for &lt;em&gt;in situ&lt;/em&gt; geochemical measurements, but those are limited to gasses like CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; (e.g., &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vaisala.com/en/measurement/carbon-dioxide-co2-measurements&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Vaisala&lt;/a&gt;) and O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; (e.g., &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.presens.de/products/detail/oxybaser-series&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PreSens&lt;/a&gt;). Others use electrochemistry to quantify concentrations of many different species (e.g., &lt;a href=&#34;https://aishome.com/in-situ-2/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Analytical Instrument Systems, Inc.&lt;/a&gt;), but data from those systems is hard to interpret and it can be impossible to deconvolve multiple overlapping signals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re working with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.qbisci.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Quantitative BioSciences, Inc.&lt;/a&gt; to develop and deploy sensor systems that use customized biosensors strains to measure a suite of contaminants. Current sensing capabilities include arsenic, lead, mercury, cadmium, nitrate, nitrite, ammonium, phosphorus, and more. We&amp;rsquo;ve deployed these systems remotely (ie, fully solar-powered and autonomous) and in harsh environments (ie, subject to driving wind, snow and temperatures from -10 to 110° F).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
