<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hydrogeology | Zach Perzan</title>
    <link>https://zperzan.github.io/tags/hydrogeology/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://zperzan.github.io/tags/hydrogeology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Hydrogeology</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://zperzan.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Hydrogeology</title>
      <link>https://zperzan.github.io/tags/hydrogeology/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biogeochemical cycling in a uranium-contaminated floodplain</title>
      <link>https://zperzan.github.io/research/riverton/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zperzan.github.io/research/riverton/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A long history of uranium mining and weapons development throughout the Cold War has left many mining, milling and testing sites contaminated with radioactive materials like uranium, thorium, and radium, as well as other non-radioactive heavy metals including vanadium, molybdenum, selenium and arsenic. There are nearly 100 such locations &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.energy.gov/lm/sites/lm-sites&#34;&gt;across the western U.S.&lt;/a&gt; managed by the Department of Energy. The groundwater contaminant plumes at many sites are not dissipating as expected and contamination may persist beyond the 100-year timeframe required for regulatory compliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contaminant plumes at many floodplain mill sites are subject to strong seasonal fluctuations, but the processes behind these variations are not well understood. We are studying uranium transport and the concurrent biogeochemical cycling that occurs during hydrologic perturbations, with research centered around a series of field experiments using artificial groundwater tracers. The tracer tests have immediate relevance to water quality concerns at the field site &amp;ndash; a uranium-contaminated floodplain in Riverton, Wyoming &amp;ndash; but has much broader implications as well. Isotopically labeled nitrate allows us to track denitrification and the production of nitrous oxide (a powerful greenhouse gas), deuterated water (D&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;2&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;O) could map plant water uptake, and dye infiltration patterns can answer questions regarding unsaturated zone flow.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
